<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Alberti Ottonis Fabri medici regii exer. Suec. Paradoxon de morbo Gallico libr. II, or, A paradox concerning the shameful disease for a warning to all against deceitful cures / translated out of the High-Dutch by Johan Kauffman.</title>
            <author>Faber, Albert Otto, 1612-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41093</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F67</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41246</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31354662</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31354662</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110222</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41093)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110222)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1739:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Alberti Ottonis Fabri medici regii exer. Suec. Paradoxon de morbo Gallico libr. II, or, A paradox concerning the shameful disease for a warning to all against deceitful cures / translated out of the High-Dutch by Johan Kauffman.</title>
                  <author>Faber, Albert Otto, 1612-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 76 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and to be had at the Corner-house of Addle- hill ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, and with print show-through and loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Prescription in manuscript tipped in at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Syphilis --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sexually transmitted diseases --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110222:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ALBERTI OTTONIS FABRI Medici Regii Exer. Suec.</hi> PARADOXON De Morbo Gallico, <hi>LIBR.</hi> II. OR, A PARADOX, Concerning the Shameful Diſeaſe. For a warning to all againſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful Cures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of the</hi> High-Dutch, <hi>by</hi> Johan Kauffman.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>This every one may read,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Not, that he to health may tread,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But acknowledge the reaſon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>VVhy we mankind</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Every where find</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our ſelves by luſt ſeiz'd on.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed and to be had at the Corner-houſe of <hi>Addle-hill,</hi> over-againſt <hi>Baynards</hi> Caſtle, 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:110222:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:110222:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas in curing of the <hi>French-Pox</hi> men have for a long time been baſely abuſed by Ignorants, <hi>Barber-Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions</hi> and <hi>Mountebanks,</hi> ſo that many Patients of high and low de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree have commonly run the hazard of their lives; therefore upon ſerious conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration I undertook to write ſomething con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it, and (if poſſible) to prevent that abuſe. Hereunto this hath chiefly moved me, That I lately cured ſeveral ſuch Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients without help of any of thoſe uſual means, and without blood-letting, purging, fluxing, bathing, ſweating, yea without Quick-ſilver and its properties, without <hi>Guaiacum</hi> and <hi>Saſſafras,</hi> or ſuch like;
<pb facs="tcp:110222:3"/>neither were they confined to their Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, nor their affairs abroad interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>And that I might aſſure them of this kind of curing, never heard before, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That it ſhould not be hurtful to them, I my ſelf have eaten and drunk that which I adminiſtred unto them. For that which ſhall conduce to the health of others, how can it be hurtful to the Phyſician? Elſe it might juſtly be ſaid to be meer deceit. A Phyſician who is ſure of his skill, will not refuſe to uſe the Medicament himſelf, which he intends that others ſhould take of him. But he that doth not ſo, nor will not, it is juſt we ſhould not have to do with him. But this is it we teſtifie, and would have taken notice of, that the Phyſician whom God hath made, may be known thereby. He that takes heed to it, goeth ſafe, and needs not fear, to hear that, wherewith a Doctor was upbraided, who miniſtred a Purge to his Patient, which wrought ſo violently, that after a hundred and fifty ſtools, he purg'd his ſoul alſo out of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.
<pb facs="tcp:110222:3"/>If ſuch Laws were made in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. That the Doctor ſhould firſt drink of his Potions, ſurely Doctors would not be ſo numerous, as now a dayes they are. I am perſwaded the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire would year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſave an Army of men for the field, which otherwaies are marching to the Church-yard. I often think, what urgent cauſe the <hi>Romans</hi> of old had, that they in that time baniſh'd the Doctors out of the City. I know not what to ſay to it. I may ſay as one did, that old <hi>Cato</hi> had counſelled them ſo to do, thereby the more to weaken the power of the Enemies of the <hi>Romans.</hi> For when they baniſhed the Doctors out of their City and Country, then were they neceſſitated to go to the Enemy. And how could they be more, effectually revenged upon their Enemies? than to ſend ſuch Butchers amongſt them. For ſome ſay, That an Army of ten thou ſand men in the Field, cannot do ſo much againſt the Enemy, as a thouſand Doctors can do among the Enemies, or in the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Countries; according to the old ſaying, <hi>A new Doctor, a new Church-yard.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:110222:4"/>I paſt once by a place where a Mountebank had ſet up his Tent, namely, in <hi>Broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreet,</hi> hard by the Cathedral Church; and I heard his Partner ſay, <hi>The Doctor is hard by, he will be here preſently.</hi> How now! (thought I) is it come to this, that the <hi>Mountebanks</hi> alſo become <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors!</hi> then ſurely the Revolution of the <hi>Romans</hi> is not far off.</p>
            <p>The reaſon why this Diſeaſe is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called the <hi>French Diſeaſe,</hi> or <hi>French-Pox,</hi> is not, becauſe the <hi>Italians, Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,</hi> or <hi>Germans, Dutch</hi> and other Nations, whatever they may be called, are freed from it: Oh no! neither is it the reaſon, as if it came originally from the <hi>French:</hi> No ſuch matter at all; for it hath been elſewhere in the world, namely, in the <hi>Indies</hi> and <hi>China,</hi> before ever it came among the <hi>French</hi> Nation. But the Name of it aroſe thus: When <hi>Charles</hi> the Eighth, King of <hi>France,</hi> in the year <hi>1493.</hi> waged war with King <hi>Alphonſus</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> about <hi>Naples,</hi> this Diſeaſe broke out firſt in the Camp of the
<pb facs="tcp:110222:4"/>
               <hi>French,</hi> and they ſay, That it came amongſt them by ſome <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who brought it firſt from the <hi>Indies,</hi> where (they ſay) it rageth Epidemically. But the <hi>Italians</hi> have given it that Name, calling it the <hi>French Diſeaſe,</hi> or <hi>French-Pox,</hi> becauſe it broke out firſt among the <hi>French,</hi> and thence it firſt was known in <hi>Europe.</hi> But the <hi>French</hi> call it after the name of the Countrey, <hi>le Mal de Naples.</hi> And therefore it is no jeer to that Nation, to call it the <hi>French Diſeaſe,</hi> or <hi>French-Pox.</hi> However to prevent miſ-underſtanding, and to ſpeak to thoſe which know no better, I have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it, <hi>The ſhameful Diſeaſe of the Privities;</hi> as from the notation of the place of the conception of this contagious Diſeaſe, which are the privy parts.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110222:5"/>
            <head>A PARADOX Concerning the <hi>Shameful Diſeaſe, &amp;c:</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">The Firſt BOOK.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of the Original of the</hi> Shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Diſeaſe.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WHen the Lord God had created Man and his Wife, he ſet them in Paradice, and commanded them,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110222:5"/>that they upon pain of death ſhould not eat of the fruit of the Tree in the midſt of the Garden; yea, they ſhould not touch it, leſt they dye. But both were naked, Man and his Wife, and were not aſhamed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Therefore we ſee even to this day, that little children are not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, though they go naked. But as ſoon as they feel in themſelves an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to the forbidden fruit, then they begin alſo to be aſhamed, and wil go naked no longer, but cover themſelves with fig-leaves.</p>
               <p n="3">3. What ſhall we then ſay to it? Shall we ſay, that the children are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed becauſe they are naked? Not ſo, but therefore, becauſe the unchaſt Luſt doth ſtir in them. Thereupon we indeed ſee in our children, that they by them actions declare the Scripture unto us, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Adam</hi> gave not a right anſwer unto the Lord God, when he ſaid, <hi>I was afraid, for I am naked:</hi> For he had no cauſe to be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110222:6"/>afraid or aſhamed becauſe he was naked, more then little children; but this is the reaſon, (as hath been ſaid) the unchaſt Luſt was ſtirring in him for to have eat of the fruit a foreſaid:</p>
               <p n="4">4. But now ſeeing that the unchaſt Luſt is the cauſe of his ſhame and fear; why then doth the Scripture ſay, <hi>they knew that they were naked?</hi> Then ſay we to it, Do the little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren not know that they are naked? Yes indeed, they know it, but they perceive it not. Therefore <hi>Adam</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo knew that he was naked, but he perceived it not.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Why ſo? becauſe his help was far off from him? O no; for it ſtands written, <hi>I will make him a help meet for him;</hi> (or as it is in the <hi>Hebrew) an help as before him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Therefore his Wife was before him naked, and without a covering, like as he alſo was; and yet he did not perceive, nor ſhe neither, that they were naked; for they knew no
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110222:6"/>more of ſhame and fear, than the little children, which we daily ſee fitting in the ſtreets naked, without ſhame and fear.</p>
               <p n="7">7. But when it came to paſs, that they liſtened more to the Serpent than to the Lord God, and their eyes were fixed on the pleaſant tree, and its fair fruits, (and this was not all, but) inſtantly they ſtretcht forth their hands and toucht them, (ah wo! now (Luſt was let looſe) they took of it, and did eat; (herewith it was done) then both their eyes were opened, and with grief they perceived that they were naked, and twiſted, or ſewed fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaves together, and made themſelves aprons.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Now they perceived that they were naked; what elſe is that to ſay, then what we ſee daily in our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, when they grow marriageable and begin to be aſhamed?</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:110222:7"/>
               <p n="9">9. Hence it is apparent, that mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riagebleneſs brings forth ſhame, but ſname cauſeth fear.</p>
               <p n="10">10. And therefore their nakedneſs was not the cauſe of their ſhame and fear, but the unchaſt Luſt, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the eating of the pleaſant fruit, was ſtirred up in them: For Wine maketh drunk; <hi>Napellus</hi> poiſoneth; <hi>Cicuta</hi> maketh mad, and the fruit of the pleaſant tree cauſeth wantoneſs. Now this Wantonneſs or Laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, being covered with the word <hi>Nakedneſs,</hi> is the Spirits modeſty.</p>
               <p n="11">11. But that the fruit of this Tree hath wrought in them the Diſeaſe of unchaſt Luſt, and hath made them drunk with Laſciviouſneſs, and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted them throughout, the Lord God teſtifieth of this when he ſaith, <hi>Who hath told thee, that thou art naked? Haſt, thou eaten of the Tree whereof I comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thee, that thou ſhouldest not eat?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. If a Flagon full of ſweet Wine ſtood on my Table, and I ſhould ſay
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110222:7"/>to my ſervant; take heed that thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rink not out of the Flagon that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>andeth on the Table; for if thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rinkeſt out of it, it will be ill with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hee. But he coveting after it, ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rink a good draught out of it, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that he reeled. And when I came home again, ſhould call, <hi>Boy, where art thou?</hi> And the Boy ſhould come crawling along on his hands and feet, and could ſcarcely ſpeak. And I ſhould ſay to him, <hi>What aileſt thou?</hi> And he ſhould anſwer me, and say, <hi>Oh Maa-ſter, I, I, I ca-ca-can not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tand:</hi> And I ſhould ſay to him, <hi>Why canſt thou not ſtand? Thon naughty Boy, haſt thou drunk out of the Flagon, which I hid thee, that thou ſhouldeſt not drink out of it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. But what would we ſay of it? We <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nfer this, that the ſweet Wine in the Flagon, which made him drunk, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to reel and ſtutter ſo, that he crawls on his hands and feet, and can ſcarcely ſpeak.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:110222:8"/>
               <p n="14">14. Therefore if <hi>Adam</hi> had not caten of the Tree, he had not been made partaker of the Tree's proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the unchaſt Luſt. And if he had not been partaker of the unchaſt Luſt, then he would not have percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his nakedneſs, but would have continued alwayes as the unmarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ageable children, without laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and conſequently without ſhame and fear: For to go naked, is no ſin, becauſe <hi>Adam</hi> and his Wife was by God himſelf not onely crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted naked, but we all after him come naked into this Wold, even unto this day. Therefore to be naked, and to go naked, is no ſin nor abomination in the eyes of God, and it was need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs for that cauſe, to be covered with Fig-leaves. But the abomination in the eyes of God is unchaſtity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the body created of God naked and pure, is defiled. Here it is, and this is it which we fain would cover<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for we are aſhamed, and are afraid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:110222:8"/>and this is the reaſon why we do it in private, in dark corners, avoiding the light, and do it by night, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be done honeſtly or diſhoneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, all will not keep off the ſhame.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Come on now ye <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> who ſay, that Luſt is no more ſin, than eating or drinking, or evacuating and voiding the excrement, becauſe the one is natural as wel as the other. Anſwer me, and ye ſhall be heard; open your mouth, that we may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, and anſwer for your ſelves; then will we tell you, whether you be in the right: Why are ye aſhamed to go naked now, more than when ye were little, and of tender years? why do not you go uncovered in your privities before all people, as the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle children do? Why are ye aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to do your need openly before all people, as well as ye eat &amp; drink, and let others look on, and are not ſhie of it? But ye creep into bawdy corners, as <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cosbi,</hi> and hide
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110222:9"/>your ſelves from the faces of men, as <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> from the face of the Lord, among the Trees in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den? Anſwer for your ſelves, and defend your cauſe; let us hear: But there is none that can ſpeak for you; neither can a rational man hear a word come from you. If I look into your boſom, there is meer laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and if I ſearch among you for a pure heart, there is none. But if there be one with a pure heart, he will not ſide with you. And it is in vain to ask you queſtions, becauſe ye cannot anſwer me. Lo ye are full of heat unto laſciviouſneſs, and liſten after things which provoke unto it, and you are tickled with it.</p>
               <p n="16">16. Is it not ſo, that your own ſoul within you, whoſe immortality is among you generally denied, bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth you before all, and checketh you unto bluſhing and ſhame? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe in you, as well as in us, is alwayes remembring her pure and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110222:9"/>chaſt immortal fleſh, which ſhe had before the eating of the fair fruit of the pleaſant Tree. And this ſhame ye can never ſhake off, though you call on all your <hi>Atheiſtical</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Whimſies to help you, yet you can be as little without ſhame, as ye can abſtain from carnal Luſt. Take notice, and be inſtructed ye ſimple ones.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Now whereas the Diſeaſe of unchaſt Luſt is come into the world, that is, into man-kind or humane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generations, through the eating of the fruit of the forbidden Tree, it is clear and manifeſt, that man is crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God pure and chaſt, without feeling of any carnal luſt-deſire in himſelf and in his fleſh; and verily we muſt be of a pure heart, if ſo be that (as it is written) we intend to ſee the face of God: And as the Scripture teſtiſieth in another place, where it is ſaid, <hi>Except ye be converted, and become as, and like to little children,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110222:10"/>ye ſhall not enter into the Kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18. And whereas now from the firſt man to us, through ſo many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable generations, this unchaſt-Luſt-diſeaſe is continually propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the ſame at the preſent hath in ſuch a manner penetrated, tinctured and thoroughly leavened our fleſh and blood, that even, as they ſay, the Philoſophers ſtone tranſmutes Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury into Gold, ſo that it doth not differ in the leaſt from other Gold; ſo now alſo our quondam chaſt and immortal fleſh and blood, through the tincture of this unchaſt Luſt is changed and altered into an unchaſt now-mortal fleſh and blood, which now differs not at all from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon mortal, created fleſh and blood of the beaſts, as Cows, Oxen and the like, in all its motions and being, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in the working of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſt Luſt-diſeaſe, and its efficacy.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:110222:10"/>
               <p n="19">19. And this is the root from whence ariſeth that Diſeaſe, which we ſpeak of.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>From whence the ſhameful Diſeaſe hath its off-ſpring.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. NOw as we have heard the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſt Luſt and Wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is ſo deep ſunk into mans nature, and is firmly united with fleſh and blood, as much as ever any Gold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>incture can be united with Mercury: and this makes out of a corruptible volatile Mercury, a fix'd Gold, perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in the fire; even ſo the Unchaſt-Luſt hath made an impure and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible body out of that, which was pure and incorruptible; ſo we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend from hence to ſearch, how out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut of it is engendered the <hi>ſhameſul Diſeaſe;</hi> and yet ſo to ſpeak of it, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110222:11"/>he, who is addicted to unchaſt Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and Converſation, may not ſo eaſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> apprehend or underſtand us, leſt he (as it is written) <hi>put forth his hand, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and alſo take of the Tree of Life, and ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> live for ever;</hi> namely, in his impure fleſhly-luſt and concupiſcence, which were an abomination above all abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, and without compare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the face of the Lord, whom no unclean perſon ſhall ſee.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When a young man is inflamed in the heat of his fleſh, and forbear and will not yeild to the inſtinct o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> provocation of his fleſh, it is a preci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous and acceptable Sacrifice before God: <hi>For they are thoſe</hi> (as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) <hi>which are not defiled with women for they are Virgins, and follow after the Lamb whitherſoever he goeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. But I ſaw a wild Buck leaping from one Hill to another, till he at laſt fell into a deep pit full of mire and ſtink, from thence he could not eſcape without boiles, naſtineſs and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110222:11"/>wounds. Now when he looked about him for a good path, he was ſtung, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re he was aware of it, by a very ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous Adder. This poyſon diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed it ſelf all over the body, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrated to the bones and marrow. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Summer if a puddle ſtand long in place, it grows ſtinking, and he that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rinketh of it, will find himſelf ill after it. And what availeth it, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſels, Diſhes and the like, are kept <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure and clean outwardly, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are full of naſtineſs and dead mens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ones? It is good fiſhing in muddy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aters, but the fiſh favour of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ud: And when Wine is mingled with water, can it again be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted?</p>
               <p n="4">4. All other Diſeaſes have one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Principle, <hi>viz.</hi> the Cure, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent forth over the Earth, whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uit and growth we muſt partake of, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> we will live; and thus we drink in the Curſe like water, againſt which we are b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to pray, <hi>viz. Bleſs theſe thy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110222:12"/>gifts O heavenly Father;</hi> for the bleſſing keeps off the curſe, but the <hi>ſhameful Diſeaſe</hi> ariſes from the fountain of the Unchaſt-luſt wherewith <hi>Adam</hi> was already overcome, and we par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> take of in him even before the earth was accurſed.</p>
               <p n="5">5. So we ſee now, that the Curſe is one thing, and the Unchaſt-luſt a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nother. The Curſe is fallen on the Earth (but not on man) contrary to Nature; but the Unchaſt-luſt is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len in Man, and hath united its ſelf to Nature: So every Difeaſe alſo generated of the Curſe, is eaſier and ſooner cured, than that which ſprings up from the Unchaſt-luſt, becauſe the other hath its Principle from the Curſe <hi>againſt Nature;</hi> but this ſprings forth out of man himſelf from the principle of Concupiſcence <hi>with Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Other Sins, which man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, are without the body, as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Idolatry, Unrighteouſneſs, Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110222:12"/>Blaſpheming, Diſobedience, Murther, Man-ſlaughter, Thieving, falſe-witneſs, and the like, as it is written, <hi>All ſins, which man commits, are without the body;</hi> ſuch are not heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary to Children, <hi>viz.</hi> If the Father hath been an Idolater, unrighteous, covetous, a Drunkard, and the like, it follows not that the Son muſt needs tread in his Fathers ſteps. But this, <hi>viz.</hi> Luſt, is inherited ever ſince the beginning of the tranſgreſſion of <hi>Adam,</hi> by all his poſterity, from children to childrens children, unceſſantly, unavoidably, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grief nor penitence can help againſt, nor deliver from it. Every child born of man, muſt follow his fathers footſteps and bear the Luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſeaſe about him as long as he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth. Therefore take heed of that Diſeaſe which is engendered thence, and conſider of it.</p>
               <p n="7">7. For the Curſe is of God incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated into the Earth, yet not eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110222:13"/>as if its Being were chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into ſomewhat elſe, but its opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was only this, as is written, <hi>That the Earth ſhould henceforth afford her ſtrength and virtue no more, but bear thorns andthiſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. But now againſt this Curſe the Bleſſing was oppoſed, whereby the thiſtles and thorns, which prick and torment us, may be rooted out again. And thus the bleſſing abundantly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-ballanceth the Curſe, ſo that the thiſtles and thorns, and the Diſeaſes which the Curſe ingendereth in us through the fruits of the Earth, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, rightly poſſeſs the point and center of life.</p>
               <p n="9">9. But the Unchaſt-luſt was of man, incorporated into man, and that eſſentially, inſomuch, that thereby the immortal being of man was changed into a mortal, ſtinking fleſh and blood, of the which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Son of God our Saviour Jeſus teſtifieth, that it availeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110222:13"/>unto eternal life, as that which cannot inherit the Kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p n="10">10. To this end and purpoſe the Regeneration was given to this fleſh and blood ſpoiled by concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and unfit for the Kingdom of God, through which new birth man is changed and fitted for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, to ſee God. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Regeneration of the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unchaſt fleſh and blood, which is received through faith, is the onely means to be ſaved.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Seeing then that the Curſe and the Concupiſcence or Unchaſt-Luſt are thus far diſtinguiſhed, that the one doth not poſſeſs man himſelf, but onely the earth, but ſo that it doth not change it, neither doth it reign over the Center of mans life with its thiſtles and thorns; but the other doth not poſſeſs the earth, but man himſelf, and that not onely rightfully, but alſo hath changed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110222:14"/>him, inſo much, that he with all his Soul, and with all his ſtrength in the Luſt-act is plunged deep into the Luſt-diſeaſe, and falls head-long in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it: What ſhall wee inferr from hence? this we will ſay, that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe which exiſteth from thence, namely the ſhameful Diſeaſe, poſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not only the point and center of life rightfully, but it dallies with the life it ſelf in the principle of Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence, and ſtands in ſuch an union that it ſeemeth impoſſible, to ſeparate the ſame from it again, unleſſe it be by an Analogiſme of Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: of this the Proverb is; <hi>Non cuivis medico contingit adire Corinthum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. And therefore becauſe the ſhameful diſeaſe ſtands in union with the life in its off Spring, namely of the fleſhly pleaſant Concupiſcence, ſuch a diſeaſe doth not preſently caſt the patient on the bed of ſicknes as other diſeaſes do, which ariſe from the Curſe, and for that cauſe cannot
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110222:14"/>attain unto a conſtant union with the life; but he may go and ſtand, eat and drink, and converſe with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther folk; in the mean while, ſuch a diſeaſe dallies with the life, and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizeth the ſame by virtue of the union of its off-ſpring with the luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful greedy fleſh, and corrodeth and gnaweth it, til at laſt it ſinketh along into ſuch putrefaction, that from henceforth no body can abide by, or be about him, by reaſon of the putrid, abominable and odious ſtink, upon which commonly death enſueth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Of the Sophiſtical Cure of the</hi> Shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Diſeaſe.</head>
               <p>BEhold, ſuch evil hath brought upon Mankind, not onely the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110222:15"/>curſe of God upon the earth, but alſo the pleaſant fruit of the Tree in the midſt of the Garden, the which then had a property, to beget or to ſtir up in him, that did eat of it, a concupiſcence permanent and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive by generation, afterwards be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come brutiſh unto all poſterity in thoſe, which are born of the blood and of the will of man, according to Scripture; from which concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence this Diſeaſe and Sickneſs that we ſpeak of, hath its deſcent and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And now as there is greater dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, to ſeparate the carnal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence or Luſtful-diſeaſe from the blood, fleſh and will of man, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the curſe from, the Earth; ſo much harder is alſo the Cure of the <hi>Shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Diſeaſe,</hi> than other Diſeaſes which come from the Curſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. So that the cure and healing of this Diſeaſe is the chiefeſt and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of all others; therefore I marvel
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110222:15"/>that thoſe which profeſs themſelves to be Phyſicians, commit ſuch to Barbers and Surgeous, whoſe limits, according to the by-word, ſhould be, <hi>Ne Sutor ultra Crepidam,</hi> The Shoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker ſhould not go beyond his Laſt.</p>
               <p n="4">4. But I think, they therefore do it, becauſe either they cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the noiſom ſtink of thoſe which are gone too far in it, or they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid that they may be infected thereby; or elſe they think, they are too good to take in hand ſuch baſe and odious Diſeaſes. But that they ſhould not know, how to cure it, I neither diſpute now, nor accuſe any; their own Writings teſtifie concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. For, they ſay, if <hi>Guajacum</hi> and <hi>Saſſafras</hi> will not help, then <hi>Mercury</hi> muſt be applied; and yet there is none of them that can with reaſon, or according to the Principle of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, affirm or maintain the Cure by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110222:16"/>
                  <hi>Mercury;</hi> but here they, with Barber-Surgeons, dance after the ſame Pipe as Empyricks, &amp; can find no ground or bottom, how carefully ſoever they ſound both here and there with their Plummet.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Neither do they deny, that this way of curing the <hi>Shameful Diſeaſe</hi> by <hi>Mercury,</hi> came originally from Barber-Surgeons, which is as much as to ſay, that it is attempted or tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed empyrick-like, without-ground and reaſon of the Art of Phyſick; and yet afterward practiſed by the literate Phyſicians; are not they then all Empyricks?</p>
               <p n="7">7. But that they might not be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for ſuch, they have carefully en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to number <hi>Mercury</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the four Qualities, to the end that they from thence might further proceed &amp; go on with it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally, according to the method of Phyſick, and ſo ſhake off the Name of Empyricks.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:110222:16"/>
               <p n="8">8. Now whereas hitherto they could not agree about it, whether its tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rament be cold or hot, yet they remain the ſame, and <hi>empyrick</hi>-like, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to cure with <hi>Mercury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. For that cauſe many renowned Phyſicians have abſtained or left off ſuch curing by <hi>Mercury,</hi> and write of the many and great evils which from thence befall the life of man.</p>
               <p n="10">10 <hi>Huttenius</hi> writes, he found by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that in his time thoſe which made uſe of ſuch a cure, not one of a hundred eſcaped, they always, firſt or laſt, had relapſes.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>Aquilianus</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial</hi> Cure is indeed a ſophiſtical or falſe Cure, and as many as he knew, they alwayes relapſed.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Torellus</hi> calls it a very dangerous Cure, full of deadly dangers; and for that reaſon men ſhould ſhun it as cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly as the Plague.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>Montanus</hi> writes, that perchance <hi>Mercury</hi> may keep back this Diſeaſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110222:17"/>for a time, yet never takes it away ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically, but it comes on again impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, like a ſtopped ſtream, and then that Patient is in a condition ten times worſe than he was before.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>Minadous</hi> ſaith, that he never ſaw one, who was fundamentally cured by <hi>Mercury,</hi> but they alwayes grew worſe afterward, and endured far worſe ſymptomes, than ever before of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten wiſhing, that they had never made uſe of it.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>Fracaſtorius, F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rnelius, Faventinus, Fallopius, Tomitanus</hi> and <hi>Sylvaticus</hi> ſay, that the Cure by <hi>Mercury</hi> is very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, a deceitful Cure, yea, an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed Cure. <hi>Helmont</hi> alſo ſpeaks in plain terms, that it is a baſe Cure, when he writes at <hi>Mercury,</hi> as long as it can be revived, by any preparation whatſoever, it is not a remedy to be uſed by an honeſt man.</p>
               <p n="15">15. What then? What ſhall we ſay of thoſe which uſe <hi>Mercury?</hi> Shall we ſay, they are baſe fellows? Far be it.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:110222:17"/>Let it rather be ſo, that they are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men, which as it is written) do not know what they do. But if ſo be that they know not what they do, and yet it is their wil and purpoſe to make whole, then they do it from a good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and may not be blamed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Law ſaith, <hi>The will and the purpoſe makes a diſtinction in Criminal things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. Though their good wil and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion keeps up their honeſty, but what is the Patient the better for it? <hi>Mercurius Vitae</hi> and <hi>Praecipitat</hi> indeed doth purge him, but not without danger; it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vomits, but Nature ſuffers wrong by it; the vital ſpirits are exhauſted, ſtrength decayeth; the Patient looks like death; the mouth breaks out ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, within it ſwelleth; his ſwallow is ſtopped; a Gangreen draws nigh, and Death ſtands at the dore.</p>
               <p n="18">18. But they ſay, We are become wiſer now, we make an unguent out
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110222:18"/>of it, therewith we annoint the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent here and there, we put him in a warm Chamber, wrap him up in a ſheet, and lay him in a good bed; this we do once or twice every day, till ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livation enſueth, and he begin to vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. But know ye nothing? Have ye not found by experience, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poplexie, Lameneſs and Palſie uſually enſue upon it? The mouth groweth ſore and raw, the tongue is enflamed, teeth looſe, and not onely much ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poiſonous ſtuff is caſt up at the mouth, but blood is alſo voided with the excrements. All which ſignifieth, that ye have done great violence to Nature and I wonder, how any Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent can endure it.</p>
               <p n="19">19. And although this Unguent be turned into a Plaiſter, that it ſhould not fall ſo tedious to the Patient, and that he may go abroad, and follow his buſineſs, yet all comes to one.</p>
               <p n="20">20. The Suffumigation is the laſt Plague, wherewith they ſeal up this
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110222:18"/>Cure, if they cannot help by other means: They make a cloſe Chamber very hot, like to a Hot-Houſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they ſet up a ſmall Tent, on which ſtands written, <hi>Carnificinaſeu Tortura,</hi> the Hang-man's room for torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: In the midſt of it there ſtands a ſtool or chair, and a cloſe Coal pan full of glowing Coals next to it. Then there is prepared for the Patient ſome comfortable food, as a couple of new-laid Eggs and a Caudle, and a draught of good Wine mixt with Conſerve of Roſes, and other Aromatical Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. Here the Patient muſt firſt drink and be refreſhed, before he is brought to the Slaughter-houſe or place of Executions then he comes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long ſtark naked without a ſhirt, and ſits on the ſtool which is cloſed round about, and behind the Tent ſtands the Barbers-man, who flings of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared <hi>Mercury</hi> one piece after another on the glowing Coales.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:110222:19"/>
               <p n="21">21. O ye Barber Surgeons and the like, ask (I pray) the Gold ſmiths, let them tell you, and the Myners will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you, and the Chymiſts know by experience, that the fume of Mercury is a deadly poyſon.</p>
               <p n="22">22. <hi>Fernelius</hi> ſaith, that he knew a Goldſmith, who meerly by the fume of <hi>Mercury</hi> fell deaf and dumb, and into a <hi>Lethargie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="23">23. <hi>Foreſtus</hi> writes, that it be fell a Goldſmiths Journey man, who being about the gilding of a ſilver Cup, the fume of <hi>Mercury</hi> ſo wrought upon him, that a ſhaking and trembling held him continually, and the hairs of his head were ſhed, and he look'd as pale as death.</p>
               <p n="24">24. <hi>Oethus</hi> relates, that a young Gentleman being troubled with Crab-Lice on his privy parts, and to rid
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:110222:19"/>them away, he annointed the place with a Mercurial Salve, whereby he was ſo much ſpoiled, that he became quite unable unto procreation.</p>
               <p n="25">25. How much more is ſuch a thing to be feared, if a Patient be for a whole hour, twice in a day, yea for a whole Week fumed therewith, that he often falls into a ſwounding Fit, and ſo muſt be pull'd out and refreſht'; but if he dieth, then they ſay, that he died of the <hi>French</hi> diſeaſe, and no man enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth further; but if it ſucceeds well, then he foameth and caſts up every day a matter of ten pounds of ſtinking, poiſonous ſtuff, till he ſpews up at laſt his ſoul alſo. For how is it poſſible that a man, who ſcarce weigheth a hundred and fifty pound weight, could hold out ſo for ten dayes together, and live; None conſiders it from whence ſuch filthy ſpittle comes, whether it come not through the Mercurial quality, and its poiſonous ferment in its corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:110222:20"/>which in the thence conceived fermentation of mans blood, breaks out in ſuch a ſtinking Flux of corrupt matter, runs on, and ceaſeth not as long as there is a drop of blood in that man's body. Oh miſery and great ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, yea raſhneſs!</p>
               <p n="26">26. But after all this, they have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented a coſtly Mercurial Water, which at laſt ſhall do the Work, yea do the Work ſo, that nothing ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main. They take ſublimed Mercury, and let it boile in a great quantity of Fountain Water, ſo that its aſtringent and acrimonious poiſonous taſte be ſcarce perceived. But I aſſure and warn every body, that whoever drinks of this Water, it wil be a Water of death unto him, which will not ceaſe to ſtir up ſtrange ſymptomes one after another, ſuch as he never felt before, piercing thorough bones and marrow, and will not ſuffer him to reſt neither day nor night, till he yeilds up his ſoul.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:110222:20"/>
               <p n="27">27. Thus is it found daily by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that many which fall into the hands of Barber-ſurgeons, fare ill, fall to ruine, and die; or are not reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to health, to the great prejudice and ſhortning of their lives, to the weakning unto death of the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrength of their vitals, by their indiſcreetly, groundleſly, uſurped Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curials, Purgings and Salivations, Bath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Sweating, letting of Blood, and the like; all which is done out of a raſh dumb blindneſs. And becauſe they are not curbed in it, they go on, grow proud, and are conceited they have great knowledge of things, inſomuch that now-a days there is not a Barber-ſurgeons Apprentice, who (as they boaſt) ſhould not know to cure the <hi>French</hi> Diſeaſe.</p>
               <p n="28">28. But tell me, good people, what is Mercury or Quick-ſilver? What is <hi>Mercurius Praecipitatus,</hi> or <hi>dulcis?</hi> What are the Flowers of Mercury, <hi>Aurum Vitae, Aquila,</hi> and whatſoever they
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:110222:21"/>may call it? Do ye know it? Who told it you? Where have ye read it? Come hither and inſtruct us, that we alſo may know it: Teach us, we wil not be aſhamed to learn; we wil atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively hearken to, and obſerve what ye ſay. But lo, ye ſtand and gape for underſtanding, as a blind man for the day-light. For you ſee, and exper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally find, that your Mercury is an unchangeable water, though ye put all kind of Masks upon him; and your Mercurial water, together with your <hi>Praecipitate,</hi> and <hi>Mercurius dulcis;</hi> what is it elſe, but a concealed poiſonous Corroſive? For why is the <hi>Sublima<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> and <hi>Arſenic</hi> a poiſon, unleſs it be by reaſon of the Corroſive, which has ſo corroded it, and turned it to a white Maſſe? Separate the Corroſive from <hi>Arſenic,</hi> then ſhall you ſee that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder is a Metal, and from the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limate,</hi> then haſt thou a running <hi>Quick-ſilver,</hi> one pound of which you may ſafely drink without hurt or good, but
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:110222:21"/>not when it was yet united with its Corroſive, and was called <hi>Mercurius Sublimatus,</hi> ſome grains whereof are enough, to bereave thee of thy life.</p>
               <p n="29">29. Hence we ſee, that Mercury without the Corroſive doth not work; for as it is poured in to the throat, ſo it runs out again below. Thus it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to an <hi>Apothecarie's</hi> Journy man, who coming home at night quite tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pl'd, went into the ſhop to take (as he uſed) a dram or two of <hi>Aqna Vitae,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his going to bed; and ſo in the dark groaping after the bottle, his ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-ſervant had removed the bottle, and ſet in the place of it a bottle of <hi>Quick-ſilver;</hi> out of it he took his draught, and went to bed; when he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened in the morning, he found in the bed that, which he drank laſt over n ght, gathered it together, and put it again into the bottle for another draught.</p>
               <p n="30">30. But if they will have the <hi>Quick-ſilver</hi> to work, either for one way or
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:110222:22"/>other, then it muſt be diſſolved in <hi>Aqua fortis,</hi> or the like Corroſive, and be reduced into ſubtile Powder, whereby the ſubtileſt and ſharpeſt part of the Corroſive in the evaporating, joins it ſelf to the <hi>Mercury,</hi> and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents it to the eyes under the mask of a red or white Maſſe, either with, or without taſte.</p>
               <p n="31">31. But as ſoon as the Corroſive, which holds it thus bound, gets away again, then is it (as before) a running <hi>Quick-ſilver:</hi> Therefore we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready told you, that <hi>Mercury</hi> is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable water, but its Corroſive is to mans body and health a dangerous poiſon, whether it ſhew its effect ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or long after, which ſometimes cauſeth a trembling and ſhaking of the members as long as the party liveth, as ye have heard already.</p>
               <p n="22">22. Seeing then that the Corroſive in ſublimed <hi>Mercury</hi> is by all held for a deadly poiſon, why then art thou, Barber-ſurgeon, ſo bold to poiſon
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:110222:22"/>any Patient with <hi>Mercurius Dulcis?</hi> Knoweſt thou not, yea thou ſhouldeſt know it; and ſeeſt thou not that the falſly up-cried <hi>Mercurius dulcis,</hi> is no other than ſublimed Mercury, which Sublimate thou and all others acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be poiſon? Or doeſt thou think that it is enough that ye put crude Mercury to the Sublimate? though the poiſonous Acrimony of the Corroſive in the Sublimate, pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trates into the crude Mercury, and ſo the whole Maſſe becomes inſipid, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s not ſweet, as thou calleſt it; is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the poiſonous Corroſive taken from it? Indeed it is diſguiſed and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with a Mask, wherewith thou deceiveſt thy Patient, and bereaveſt him of his life, according to thine own confeſſion; for the reaſon that <hi>Metcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius dulcis,</hi> whether it be ſharpiſh or ſweet, that is, without taſte, turns not again unto <hi>Quick-ſilver,</hi> is, becauſe the Corroſive of the Sublimate binds him.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:110222:23"/>
               <p n="33">33. Go therefore, and learn not to diſſolve, but to coagulate Mercury in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a brittle Maſſe, ſo that it may be ground and beaten, and not be able to turn again into <hi>Quick-ſilver,</hi> though the Corroſive be nearly and cleanly ſeparated from it; and then boaſt that thou haveſt a <hi>Mercurius Praecipitaetus</hi> and <hi>dulcis,</hi> wherewith thou canſt cure the <hi>French</hi>-Pox. But ſurely this wil be hid from thine eyes, and Mercury will be to thee an unchangeable Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p n="34">34. In the mean while take notice ye Patients, and be not deceived, it concerns you; for they do not care, whether you live or dye. And ſeeing it is a Diſeaſe, of which you are aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and would hide, therefore they are the more bold, to torment you with their Corroſive <hi>Mercury,</hi> whether you live or die.</p>
               <p n="35">35. And that ye may rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand me, I wil ſpeak in plain terms We call Corroſive a Water like an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quafort,</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:110222:23"/>or the like, which eats all in pieces, and turns it to a ſlime, be it Steel, Cloath, Iror, Linnen, Quickſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Pearls, Corals, Stones, or any thing elſe. The Vulgar ſort of <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> call this, a Diſſolving, and I call it a corroding, eating in pieces and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ſlime or duſt. Now when the Corroſive turns to ſlime the ſaid things, it's ſharpeſt parts by degrees faſten on the atoms or particles that it corrodes, and unites or binds it ſelf therewith firmly, that although after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the remaining weak Corroſive Water be evaporated with a ſtrong fire, yet that ſame Corroſive power or quality wil not leave the corroded I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron or Mercury, and beſtows on it an a crimonious and ſad bitter taſt, which the ignorant ſeek to conceal by adding of freſh Mercury; and this ſhall be then your Medicament.</p>
               <p n="36">36. Be it therefore known unto you, that as long as out of the ſtomach there doth not come into your body
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:110222:24"/>any ſowre Acrimonie, or Corroſive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciditie, you are in health; but as ſoon as there is a Corroſive admitted, fleſh and blood abhors ſuch a ſtrange gueſt, and begins to tremble at it, and in caſe it cannot ſhake it off, nor without help cannot expel it, then this Corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>five proceeds according to the nature of its poiſonous property, and cauſes a putrefaction and rottenneſs in the fleſh and blood; which from day to day, and from year to year unpercei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vably encreaſeth ſo much, til there be no more help for it. But the like cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſive ariſeth alſo out of the carnal concupiſcence, or Luſt-diſeaſe, from which in the privy part ariſes a ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing corroſive quality, which by degrees ſlips into the blood and fleſh, where the Luſt-diſeaſe keeps its reſidence, and becomes one with it, <hi>propter Symbolum,</hi> from thence is uſhered in a radical pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction of the fleſh and blood in man, which commonly is called the <hi>French</hi>-diſeaſe.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:110222:24"/>
               <p n="37">37. Now obſerve concerning the Corroſive of ſublimed Mercury, how it penetrates into the crude Mercury added to it, and ſo diſperſeth it ſelf, that the former auſtere and bitter taſte of the ſublimate is altogether unperceivable on the tongue; but the hurtful Corroſive is not therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, but hideth his poyſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous quality in the added freſh Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury, by way of extenſion. Now when ye take inwardly ſuch inſipide ſublimate, in caſe the ſtomach is ſtrong enough, then it keeps the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſive in awe, or vomits it up, and ſuffers it not to have its will. And this is the reaſon that ſometimes one eſcapes out of ſuch a dangerous Cure, and gets away, whether he be ſound or no.</p>
               <p n="38">38. And in caſe he thinks that he is again in health, then let him know, that even as the Corroſive of the Sublimate is drawn into the Crude Mercury, which is added, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:110222:25"/>is become inſipid, and for that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is thenceforth called <hi>Mercurius dulcis;</hi> ſoalſo may the Corroſive of the <hi>ſhameful Diſeaſe</hi> drawn into the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curius dulcis,</hi> and not to be percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; but the gnawing poyſon and corroſive of the <hi>French Pox</hi> is not therefore taken away, though its poiſonous putrifying quality be for a time allayed by the addition of <hi>Mercurius dulcis;</hi> and this appears, becauſe the ſame putrifying quality again manifeſts it ſelf by little and little, in all manner of new ſymp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms, the quality of the Mercury be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſperſed and expired, then the gnawing poiſon of the <hi>French</hi> Diſeaſe gets looſe again, and begins to rage as formerly; yea ſometimes, when Nature is too weak, to drive out wholly the <hi>Mercurius dulcis,</hi> it ſtirs up greater and more dangerous ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes than there were before; whereby the Patient learns to know how he was deceived by a palliating cure.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:110222:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Of the right way of curing the</hi> Shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Diſeaſe.</head>
               <p>Htherto have we proved, that the <hi>Shameful Diſeaſe</hi> hath its origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal not from the Curſe of the earth, as other diſeaſes, but from a luſtful Corroſive, and this Corroſive from the Concupiſcence of the fleſh, or laſt diſeaſe, and the fleſhes concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence from the pleaſant fruit of the Paradiſical Tree, even before the curſe went out over the earth; we have alſo made known, what kind of remedies they are, wherewith Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber-ſurgeons, Hot houſe-keepers and Mountebanks, and ſuch like, have hitherto gone to work with pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liative Cures; and there remains ſomething to be ſpoken concerning the right and ſundamental Cure.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And if therefore the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate cauſe of the ſhameful Diſeaſe is not indeed the concupiſcence of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:110222:26"/>or Luſt-diſeaſe, which cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be rooted out without the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation of the corrupted body in death, but the from thence ariſen Corroſive, which conſequently cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſuch a putrefaction of the fleſh, it is eaſie to underſtand, that if the luſtful Corroſive be cured or taken away, then the effect alſo is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; and that then alſo the from thence derived putrefaction muſt ceaſe, and may be removed by the nature of the Archeiſh powers of man, without any further help.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Now the aboliſhing of the luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Corroſive conſiſts in its being mortified: And this is the cure of the <hi>French</hi> diſeaſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And that ſuch mortifying can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be effected with Mercury and its Corroſives, we have already proved. Neither will <hi>Guajacum, Sarſaparilla de Guajaquil, Saſſafras, Smilax, China, and Saponaria,</hi> or the like, promiſe us any help for it: Purging, Bathing, or
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:110222:26"/>Houſes, Sweating, or letting of Blood, weaken the body no leſs than the <hi>Venus</hi> it ſelf, according to the old Proverb: <hi>Corpora debilitant, Balnea, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a, Venus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. How now? Do we reject the uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al means of Phyſick? What elſe is there beſides Purging, Bathing, Sweating and Blood-letting, from which diſeaſes flye, as the Devils flie from Frankinſence? But we oppoſe the ſhameful diſeaſe by mortifying of its venereal Corroſive; and we need none of the Hot-houſe-keepers, we regard not purging, ſweating, nor keeping within Chamber, though it were in the midſt of Winter, and we reſt content, that we deſtroy and kill the Corroſive of the diſeaſe, that is, that we deſtroy its foundation, though the patient do not come all the Winter long into a warm Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
               <p n="6">6. When a City is beſieged, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the means for life, <hi>viz.</hi> Victuals,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:110222:27"/>Wood, Corn and the like, are kept out, and I would help them by ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Proviſion through the Enemies Camp, would not all men call me a fool? Becauſe I ſhould thereby do more hurt than advantage to the City, becauſe through my relief the Enemy would be ſtrengthened? So do all thoſe, that will cure a patient of the ſhamefull Diſeaſe by admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring of ſuch means, through which the luſtful Corroſive, which beſieged mans health, is rather ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p n="7">7. But what is then to be done? namely thus, deſtroy, or drive away the enemy from the City, or bring ſuch a relief and ſuccour into it, that they themſelves may beat him; that is, the Luſtful Corroſive, as the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, muſt be deſtroyed, then the ſiege will ceaſe.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Are there other Ceremonies needful? For I hold it to be need leſs to open the Gates for them, that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:110222:27"/>they might go in and out; nor to bring meat and bread to them, they themſelves will fetch it; or to build again their battered houſes, which themſelves know better, than a ſtranger. For Nature, when once ſhe is releaſed or delivered of the ſiege, knoweth beſt, how to repair her ſelf without any further help.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Now if ye ask, What is then the mortification of the Luſtful Corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive? how is it done? I will ask you one word alſo, anſwer me, then will I tell you, what it is, and how it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered: Are ye made Doctors of God, or of men? Anſwer me. But ye think with your ſelves, we ſay, We are made Doctors of God; then will he ſay, Why do ye not know this thing? But if we ſay, Men have made us Doctors for money and good words, then men wil make no more uſe of us; for they know that it is written, <hi>Deus creavit Medicum,</hi> God hath made the Phyſician. And
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:110222:28"/>they anſwer and ſay: What is that to thee? Well then, neither will I tell you, how this luſtful poyſon is mortified, nor how it is to be mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
               <p n="10">10. But to you that have need of it, which ſigh after it, and ſeek for help with grief and repentance; I will tell to you, to you will I tell it, that you may have cauſe to rejoice, in the ſecond part of this book.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Therefore obſerve what I ſay, take notice of what I write, confider it, and ſearch into it, then ye may be helped. For when I was young, a ſtrange thing befel me, and my ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were raviſhed with it. I walked toward the Eaſt, through a thick forreſt, it was duskiſh &amp; dark, round about me, and I went aſtray. Then I eſpied a ſtrong Caſtle on a high Mountain in the midſt of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, which afar off was like unto a fair Chryſtal, of one piece: I thought to make haſt unto it, to view it, but
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:110222:28"/>could find no way, which might bring me thither: For what way ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I turn'd, every where it was full of buſhes and thorns, there was no paſſing through. Then one took me by the hand, but I ſaw him not; and he ſaid to me. <hi>Follow me, and open thine eyes:</hi> And ſo we went along with one another. Then I eſpied a round beam ſaid over a narrow, quick and deep ſtream, no leaning on either ſide. I came to it, and ſaw a blind man led with a ſtring by a Dog, ſetting his foot on the round beam to paſs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. And when I beheld it, I thought what will come of him; by and by I ſaw another blind man coming from the other ſide, led by a dog, and they met on the midſt of the beam. Now when the two Dogs, which led them, thruſt againſt one another, and neither of them would give way, they began to ſnarl, and fought; immediately they fell off from the beam, and pull'd after
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:110222:29"/>them the two blind men; they plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into the water, and were carried away by the ſwiftneſs of the ſtream, ſo I loſt them out of my ſight. And he that led me by the hand, ſaid to me, <hi>So it is, when the blind lead the blind, both fall into perdition. But be thou care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and ſhake not, we will get over ſafe enough.</hi> Whilſt he was ſetting his foot on the beam, I pull'd back my hand, but he pull'd me after, &amp; held me faſt. And when we were on the midſt of the beam, I ſeeing the ſtream paſs ſo ſwiftly underneath, the Earth run round with me, and was ready to fall off. Then my eyes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, and I perceived, that he which led me by the hand, had two great wings, wherewith he kept us equally ballanced, and could not ſlide off. But inſtantly we were over. And it was with me as with one that awakened out of a deep ſleep, and was heartily glad, that it was not ſo as he had dreamed. And I ſaid to
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:110222:29"/>my Companion, Whither do we now go further? But there was no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply; I expected an anſwer, but all was ſilent: Then I pull'd my hand, and no body held it. I thought, was I then in a dream? And I looked back on the ſwift ſtream, and ſaid to my ſelf, This, this is the beam I paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over, and this is the ſtream I was ſo ſhie off; I am awake, and not in a dream, Where is then my Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? There was no anſwer, all ſilence. Then went I ſtraight forward, and came directly to the Caſtle, which I had ſeen on the other ſide of the water. I ſtood and admired at its great luſtre, and at the fair Fabrick: I looked after the Gate, and went round about, but could not find it. Then I grew ſad, and ſate under a Tree, and ſtill caſt up my eyes to the fair Caſtle, till I unawares fell into a ſleep. And me thought, I ſaw an old man look out of a Window, which beckned to me with his finger; La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:110222:30"/>and came nearer: Then he let down a Rope, which I laid hold on, and he drew me up in a moment: Then I awakened, and ſaid, This was a dream. I aroſe and would go; and behold I ſtood in the midſt of the Caſtle, in the Court of it. For as I ſaw now, the Caſtle was built round, and in the midſt thereof there was a fair Court, in its center or middle, point there ſtood a deep Well, coſtly adorned with all manner of fair fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures and ſtatues.</p>
               <p>In the middle of the Well there ſtood the image of the Sun, like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bright glittering Gold, when its melted; but in the midſt it was blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and therein it ſtood. <hi>Perſectio,</hi> and a cypher by it.</p>
               <p>Beneath about the edge of the Well there ſtood the <hi>Statue of Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> (ſuch was the inſcription) paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of a glittering red, and had a yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Cane in his hand; On it ſtood written with ſilver Letters: <hi>Electrum
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:110222:30"/>immaturum;</hi> and on the other ſide, <hi>Agens Naturae;</hi> and above: <hi>Drachmae duae,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next to this ſtood the <hi>Statue of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn,</hi> painted black, and had in his hand a grey glittering ball, on which ſtood: <hi>Coagulatio ſecunda,</hi> and underneath: jv. and xij.</p>
               <p>Next followed <hi>Jupiter,</hi> painted pale yellow, and had in his hand a flaming Croſs, on which ſtood writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: <hi>Coeteris venenum;</hi> and in the midſt ſtood: xij and iv.</p>
               <p>Then came <hi>Mars</hi> painted of a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-colour, and had a bow in his hand, bent; and anarrow laid upon it, with this Superſcription: <hi>Indigus indigentibus ſubſidio,</hi> and beneath ſtood: <hi>Nam</hi> xiv and ij.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> alſo was preſent, painted green, fair in the higheſt degree, and covered her privy part with her hand, over which ſtood written: <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li me tangere,</hi> and on the hand: <hi>Cave, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Caves,</hi> and beneath viij and viij.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:110222:31"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luua</hi> ſmiled, was painted green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blew, and with her right arm ſhe reached after the Sun, on which ſtood written: <hi>Nondum perfecta. Nam</hi> II and XIV.</p>
               <p>Now when I had viewed theſe Statutes, I thought, how am I thus come among the Heathen Gods, it ſeems as if I were in a Heathen Kings Houſe! Yet I ſet down their inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in my Table-book, and ſtepped nearer unto it, and would alſo my ſelf look into the Well: but as ſoon as I leaned over it, and lookt into it, an inviſible ſume ſmote my face, that upon a ſudden I loſt both ſight and hearing. I ſuddenly ſtept back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and ſtood long before I could fetch breath: my eyes run over, and I was tickled in my noſtrils. When I came to my ſelf again, me thought I had ſeen flames of fire beneath in the Well, and had a good mind to look in again, that I might learn the very truth of it; I thought, How
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:110222:31"/>ſhall I go about it? I wil keep in my breath, and uſe Spectacles to ſave my eyes. Being thus cautiouſly arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I ſtepped thither again, and would look into it; but behold, there aroſe a fume out of the depth of the Well, which fill'd all the Caſtle-Court, in manner of a ſtinking miſt, inſomuch that I could not ſee at all; onely above on the brim about the Well, it ſtood written: <hi>FONS IG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIS SINE QUO NON.</hi> But the myſt which came up out of the Well, was ſo great, thick and ſtrong, that I was forced to be gone: <hi>I</hi> run up and down in the Caſtle from door to door, and knockt, to ſee whether one or other would open to let me in, for <hi>I</hi> was almoſt choaked. Then one door opened, when <hi>I</hi> run by, and <hi>I</hi> was pull'd in ſuddenly, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it was locked again; it was a black fellow in Linnen breeches, without a doublet, he ſweated all his face o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and he ſaid to me, <hi>Sit down, I
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:110222:32"/>drink to thee;</hi> for he had a pot of been in his hand: <hi>I</hi> ſaid, Much good may it do you. He ſaid, but how com'ſt thou hither? Who hath let thee in? I anſwered and ſaid, <hi>I</hi> do not know it my ſelf; <hi>I</hi> wiſh <hi>I</hi> were out again; He anſwered and ſaid, <hi>Pray do not grieve becauſe the fume hath nipped thee a little; doſt thou not ſee how I look?</hi> And <hi>I</hi> ſaid, <hi>Are ye a coal-burner?</hi> He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered me and ſaid: <hi>Yes, thou haſt hit it, I am a Coal-burner; for in my time I have conſumed well a hundred Load of Coales,</hi> and ſmiled. <hi>I thought indeed</hi> (ſaid <hi>I) that ye could not look ſo like a Smith for nothing. But what kind of mad Well is that which ye have in the Court?</hi> He anſwered me and ſaid, <hi>The Well is not mad, but it is a Well of Life unto thoſe, which ſtand by it; and he that draweth out of it, and drinketh, he is healed thereby, though he had the French diſeaſe.</hi> But <hi>I</hi> anſwered to him, and ſaid, <hi>Yea a Well of death, for it coſt me almoſt my life, when I would but onely look into it.</hi> He
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:110222:32"/>anſwered me and ſaid, <hi>My Son, too much is nought: The Well is good, and without this Well we cannot make ſire, but onely we know how to deal carefully with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. I</hi> ſaid, <hi>How muſt one do it? For when I came a little near to it, it beat into my face, that I could neither ſmell nor ſee, and I thought no other but that I muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eild up my Ghoſt in the very place.</hi> He anſwered me and ſaid, <hi>We have a ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken rope, therewith we let down the bucket, and thus we draw and pull it up again. We do not come ſo near unto it; but we ſtand off a little way. How can ye then</hi> (ſaid <hi>I) ſtand ſo long in the Court, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſtrong myſtie fume?</hi> He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered and ſaid, <hi>That's no matter, as ſoon as the Sun is high, and ſhines clear, then the myſt falls. Thou art come to it a little too ſoon. Why</hi> (ſaid J) <hi>do ye uſe a ſilken rope, and not rather an Iron chain?</hi> but he anſwered: <hi>no, Iron can reſiſt this water; for its nature and quality is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful; all Mettals melt in it, as Butter melts in warm water. We could never fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:110222:33"/>its depth, and its ſtrength and virtue is every morning new; it keeps conſtantly in one vigor, and all poyſon digeſted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, turns inſtantly unto a wholeſom Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament.</hi> J ſaid, <hi>Then I pray you, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part ſome of it unto me. Very willingly;</hi> ſaith he, and gave me a whole bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle full, and told me withall, how J ſhould uſe it. And many other things he told me of this Well, and of this Caſtle; but J took my leave of him, and he brought me into a deep Cellar, there was a ſubterrane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſecret way, which was paved with all ſort of precious ſtones, with Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buncles, Diamonds and Saphirs, Smaragds, Rubies and Topaz, which caſt ſuch a luſtre, whereby this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean paſſage was bright &amp; light: And J ſaw that it was above, and at both ſides full of fair pieces of Gold Oar, Mineral Cinober, and Silver Oar, Oar of Lead, Pewter, Loath-and iron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, betwixt there hung here and there yellow ice-ſickles. J beheld all
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:110222:33"/>with admiration, and thought, this is indeed a rich Myne, or Metalline Rock; ſuch another Myne-work may happily not be in the World: And at laſt we went thorough a long paſſage, till we came to a door; there he knocks, and gave the word, which I underſtood not; and the door went open: There I eſpied through a little hole, the day-light afar off; but when we came to it, it was of that bigneſs that one could creep through it; but there lay a great ſtone before it, which he knew to remove ſo nimbly, that I could not perceive how he did it; then J crep out with my bottle, and unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily J gave it a knock at the ſtone, and it broke: J called back, Oh good Sir, the Bottle is broken, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to turn about; but lo, he put the ſtone before it as nimbly as he had removed it, and for my life J could not rowl it away; J call'd, but he would not hear, for he was gone.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:110222:34"/>
               <p>And now as J went a little farther, J paſſed through a fair large field, to a great High-way, where many Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons laden with Coales and Glaſſes were drawn before me; J followed them, and came into a great City, which lay betwixt two Mountains, on a fair plain, and was called <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flers-thal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was an Univerſity full of Students, and there were neither Doctors nor Profeſſors, but every one was of himſelf to learn what, he would know, without a Maſter. And this Univerſity was called <hi>Autodoxia,</hi> and over the Gate it ſtood written: <hi>Inſudore vultus tui.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And juſt in the Entry, at the right hand, there lay about a hundred Load of Coales; at the left hand J ſaw many broken Pots and Pans, Crucibles, Retorts, Glaſſes &amp; Stacks, on a heap as great as a Hill; J thought, J have ſeen ere now among Myne-Works, ſuch a heap of ſlacks, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:110222:34"/>ſaid, Surely here muſt be ſome melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-houſe or other: And juſt as J entered, J ſaw a Boy with a Lap full of broken Pans and Glaſſes paſſing on, who looked like a young Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith: J asked him, What is here to do? But he grinn'd with his teeth like a Negro, and ſmiling, ſaid, Come in hither, and thou ſhalt ſee it: J went in, and behold there ſtood ſo many Furnaces, and the like ſtuff, that J could not tell them; they blowed, they melted, they reverbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, they diſtilled out of bodies, great and ſmall; out of Sand, in <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neo;</hi> they forced out of Retorts into large Receivers; they ſet things in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion; one poured coals into the <hi>Piger Henricus,</hi> another ſtood luting; J ſaw diſſolving, ſiltring, fixing, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hobing, calcining, volatizing, ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, granulating, as many tearms, ſo many divers works, and who could tell them all. J ſtept to one, whom J thought to be the chief Journey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:110222:35"/>who juſt then took out a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort; and J ſaid to him: God ſave you, what are ye a doing? He lookt on me with a ſquint eye, and ſaid, Thou ſeeſt what we do, thou needſt not ask; and ſo he broke the Retort in two, and took out the <hi>Caput mortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</hi> And another was taking a Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fible out of the fire, and when it grew cold, he broke it in pieces. A third ſtruck at a boy with a ſtick, and hit a great Receiver, which flew in a hundred pieces. Then J anſwered and ſaid: Now J ſee indeed, what ye are doing, ye break Cruſibles and Glaſſes, and beſides burn an abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of coales. One among them anſwered me and ſaid: This we can do beſt, and never miſs, though we hit nothing elſe. Then there came one behind me and pull'd me by the ſleeve and ſayd: <hi>allons Monſieur, aydes moy à Souffler,</hi> and ſo reached to me a pair of bellowes. <hi>By</hi> and by an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther calld to me, pray good fellow,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:110222:35"/>hold this Glaſs a little, until <hi>I</hi> empty this reaceaver. Another ſaid to me, Who are you? Come, fling a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or two of coals into the Furnace. To be ſhort, in a little time my half ſhirt was as black as a Smiths boy, and I looked as black as they. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I liked the fooliſh Work well enough, ſo that I tarried by it above twenty years, then I returned home.</p>
               <p>My Fathers Name was <hi>Autogenes,</hi> and my Mothers Name was <hi>Hethia;</hi> but he dyed a little before J came, and my mother followed another man, and went away with him; my eldeſt Siſter was yet alive, but ſhe knew me not. J told her, who J was; then ſhe leapt for joy, and ſaid, O my Brother <hi>Chryſogenes,</hi> art thou he? Our Fathers Corps is embalmed to keep it from putrifying, that thou ſhould'ſt ſee it: come hither, and ſee where he lieth, for thou ſhalt find there thine inheritance. J ſaid, Yea
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:110222:36"/>Siſter, I am no ignoramus alſo, I have not ſpent my time idly among ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in for reign parts; J can fix <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury, I</hi> have many brave Albations, which hold the teſt. J can make fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Lnna: I</hi> can do more yet, <hi>I</hi> can make Gold; but take heed, that you do not tell it others, elſe it wil coſt me my life.</p>
               <p>And we went together into the Vault where he lay; and my Siſter ſaid to me. My Brother, J wildeclare unto thee all the Treaſures of our Father, which he hath left unto us, and ſaid to me: <hi>Argenis,</hi> abide by thy Brother. Now therefore promiſe firſt unto me, That thou wilt not forſake nor leave me all the dayes of thy life. And I made promiſe to her. Then ſhe took up my Fathers Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-ſheet, and uncovered the middle part of his Corps; there his ſtomach lay naked, and this Epitaph was written upon it:
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:110222:36"/>
                  <q>AUTOGENES. PALINGENIUS. FILIO. MEO. CHRYSOGENI. SACRUM. IN. HOC. SCRINIO. RELINQUO. TIBI. REGENERATIONIS. ANALO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GON. NAM. POST. MULTAS. AMBAGES. ET. VANOS. LABORES. TANDEM. REDIBIS. AD. ME. ET. QUOD. QUAERIS. INVENIES.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Argenis</hi> ſaid: Here, here we have it: She drew out a knife, and ſaid, Here <hi>Chryſogenes,</hi> cut up, and let's ſee, what is in it. And when I put the knife to it, and would anatomize the ſtomach, ſomething ſtirr'd in it like a child in the womb. However, I made an inciſion, and a hole in it; but preſently it hiſſed, and a ſtrong ſcent came out. But when I made the hole of the ſtomach ſomewhat
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:110222:37"/>wider, we perceived that it was ful of Vermine, and among them we ſaw a very neſt of Lizards, all of them were as yellow as Brimſtone, and look'd hard upon us. We were ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and ſaid to one another, it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well analogized; He is full of ſtink and worms, and we were ready to run away. Inſtantly the Lizards went aſſunder, and came out of the hole, the one run this way, the other that way. There in that place whers the Lizards lay in the ſtomach, we perceived a white Serpent which had a golden Crown upon her head and a gilded Croſs on her forehead and was to look on, as fine ſilver on the Teſt, when it glitters like the fair Evening-ſtar, when it riſeth, ſo bright and glittering it looked. We indeed could no ſooner ſpie it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lizards lay or ſate upon her, like a Hen that ſits upon her Eggs. And when I eſpied the golden Crown, then I remembred the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:110222:37"/>Crown, of which there is ſo much talk, and would fain have had it. The Serpent began to ſtretch her ſelf, and would be gone alſo. But I took courage, and knew not how, as when one goeth in the dark, and it ſeemeth to him, as if he ſaw a ſpirit, and falls upon it, when he ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther give way; ſo I alſo fel on, and fled not from the Serpent, but caught her juſt by the Crown, and pull'd her out. Indeed ſhe ſtruggled a little, but as ſoon as ſhe felt the freſh air, ſhe yeilded up her Ghoſt, and dyed. I ſaid to my Siſter: <hi>Argeniis,</hi> What ſtrange Treaſures are theſe? if thou hadſt no other thing to dſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover unto me, I had ſaved my oath that you took of me. The Serpent's Crown may perchance be worth ſomething, if one knew how to uſe it; but as touching the Serpent, I have heard ere now, that the powder of Serpents is good againſt poiſon; but how is it made? <hi>Argenis</hi> anſwered
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:110222:38"/>and ſaid, My dear brother, I know not what to ſay to it. This I know well, and have often with my ears heard, that our Father uſed to ſay at the Table: O would to God, that <hi>Chryſogenes</hi> came home before I dye. For I fear, that he wil ſpend his time idly where he is; he is my Son, and I am his Father. He muſt learn to know me, and have of me that, which he looks for. Yet tell him, <hi>Argenis,</hi> if I do not live at his return, that he ſhall ſeek in me, and in my Entrails, there he ſhall find his portion, and the Treaſure ſought by many, and found by few. Now <hi>Chryſogenes,</hi> thou thy ſelf ſeeſt, that I thought no other but that we ſhould find ſome ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar thing here. Therefore I pray thee, blame me not, I wil willingly acquit thee of the Oath. Now whileſt we ſtood thus amazed, the Maid-ſervant came running; and ſaid: Miſtriſs, it is time, the Oven is hot, and the dow is ready to be ſet in. <hi>Argenis</hi> had juſt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:110222:38"/>the dead Serpent in her hand, and ſo in haſt went to the Baking troff very thoughtful, and put her hands into the dow, to make the bread, but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got the dead Serpent in her hand, and ſo thruſt it among the dow. I ſtood afar off, and call'd: Siſter, what doſt thou? But it was too late. We ſearched all the Dow to find the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent again, but could not. The Dow began to ſwel, and came almoſt over the troff. Then they muſt to kneed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, breaking, and working of the Dow. The Loaves were made and ſet in, and the Oven cloſed, as is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual.</p>
               <p>In the mean time we went again to the Vault, where the Corps of our deceaſed Father did lye, intending to make farther ſearch. When we came thither without a Candle light (for we were perplext) we found his Corps no more; we groaped in the dark after it, but found it not. And whilſt we were perplext at it, lo in
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:110222:39"/>the Vault, it was as light as day; and from that place where he lay, there came a voice out of the earth, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: What ſeek ye the living among the dead? O ye fools, and of ſlow hearts, to underſtand all whatever the wiſe have ſpoken. Have yee not your ſelves carryed him away, do ye not know then, where ye layd him? Then fear and trembling ſeized on us, and wee runn away, and knew not, what to make of it.</p>
               <p>The Maid-ſervant call'd: Miſtriſs where are ye? I am afraid the bread in the Oven burns, wil ye not once look to it? But J believe you have tarried too long already. <hi>Argenis</hi> ſaid: Alas! J did not think once of it, and run haſtily to the Oven. But as the Maid had ſaid, ſo it was, the bread was burnt, and turn'd to a black brown bisket, onely fit to be thrown away; and it was flung in the hogs-waſh which is given to the Swine. Now at that time there was
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:110222:39"/>a great <hi>Murrain</hi> among the Hogs, of which they died as fait as of a plague: and we had then above twenty hogs, which vvere all ſick. Now vvhen the maid ſerved them vvith that waſh, they ſucking it in, all recovered at once. And vvhen vve look'd into the waſh, it was as red as Claret. J ſaid, how comes this to paſs? Surely the burnt bread hath cauſed this; for there is nothing flung in there, but what comes from the waſhing of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes. J run to the baking Oven, and found one cruſt, which J ſoaked in wine, which made it blood-red. J gave of it to one of my neighbours to drink, who lay deadly ſick, and he recovered at that very hour. J drank of it, &amp; me thought <hi>I</hi> was nevv born. <hi>Argenis</hi> alſo drank of it, and it made her ſhed her white-grey hairs, and gold-yellow hairs grevv in their place, and ſhe found her ſelf in her ſtrength, as a maid of tvventy years.</p>
               <p>Then J thought upon vvhat vvas
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:110222:40"/>paſt, and my eyes were opened, that J underſtood all, what we had igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly done. Thereupon we gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the remaining crumbs out of the Oven, and carefully ſcraped the Dow-tub, and kept it ſafe together. J put it all into a Box of ivory, and wrote upon it: <hi>REGENERATION IS ANALOGON.</hi> And vvhen J baked, put a little of it into the Dovv in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Leaven, and it laſted me a long time. When my good friends came to me, <hi>I</hi> let them drink of it. But vvhen it became knovvn, J could not be quiet; all thoſe vvhoſe Hogs vvere ſick, came running to me, to let them have ſome of it, <hi>&amp;c. Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua deficiant, donceſe quantur, interim.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:110222:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:110222:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:110222:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
